Moustakis Family Papers MS082
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Moustakis Family Papers
1909 -- 1929
1880 -- 2006
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Moustakis, Constantine Christou
MS082
4.85 Linear Feet 6 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 3 series: Correspondence and family material; Photographs and films; and Published material.
Custodial History
The majority of this collection was donated by Christy Moustakis' widow, Liz Moustakis in 1990. Some materials were also donated by George C. Marcopolous, Tufts Professor of History and first cousin once removed of Constantine Moustakis and second cousin of Christy C. Moustakis, in 2003 and 2008. Exact provenance and donor information can be found in collection documentation.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, clippings, photographs, and other materials of the Moustakis family. The bulk of the collection pertains to the political activities of Constantine C. Moustakis and his Christy. Constantine was a Greek nationalist living in the United States with connections to Calvin Coolidge and the Republican Party. Christy was a Trotskyist political activist and writer. He joined the Socialist Workers Party in the late 1930s and became a volunteer body guard for Leon Trotsky in Mexico in 1940. Photographs in the collection show the Trotsky compound at Coyoacán, just outside of Mexico City, as well as Trotsky himself.
Biographical / Historical
Constantine Christou Moustakis (1883-1925) was born at Longaniko, (Sparta), Greece, on February 15, 1883, the son of Christos Moustakis (d. 1930) and Nikoletta Demarkes (d. 1940). He emigrated in 1897 to the United States with his older brothers George (1877-1958) and Nicholas (1880-1969), settling first at Lowell, MA, where they worked in mills.
In 1905 the three brothers purchased a confectionery store at 220 Essex St., Salem, with a candy counter and a tea room, and the three moved to Salem. Originally the store was called "The Palace of the Sweets," but later became known as just "Moustakis Brothers." Around 1910 two other brothers, John (1894-1979) and Louis, newly arrived from Greece, joined the firm, which lasted from 1905 to 1968, known primarily for the manufacture of quality confections and candy.
In November, 1909, Constantine married Gertrude Russell Putnam, born in 1891, the daughter of Charles Henry Putnam (b. 1847) and Martha E. Wescott (1855-1942). They had three children all born in Salem: Christy Constantine Moustakis (February 11, 1911 to October 20, 1989); George Constantine Moustakis (August 15, 1913 to February 5, 1993); and Priscilla Constantine Moustakis (Babas) (born August 2, 1915). Gertrude Putnam Moustakis died young on October 1, 1918.
It is said that in 1911 Constantine Moustakis organized at Salem what was perhaps the first 'Holy Legion of Greek-American Youth' for service to their native land in view of the troubles that were developing in the Balkans. Brothers George and John remaining behind to manage the business, while Constantine and his brothers Nicholas and Louis departed for Greece in December 1912, arriving in January, 1913. While in Greece he assiduously wrote to his wife Gertrude in English.
As a soldier Constantine's excellent command of English soon got him attached to the Greek Government's "Bureau de la Presse" in Salonika, where he wrote newspaper dispatches for the The New York Times and The Manchester Guardian. Upon completing his military service at the end of war, he returned in September 1913 to his young family, his second son having been born during his absence. His brothers also returned to resume their residence and work at Salem, though Louis returned later because of an injury sustained in battle.
Upon his return home, Constantine edited his remembrances and dispatches of the war into an unpublished manuscript, giving lectures to various social and men's groups in and around Salem. He illustrated his talks using glass negatives slides, including a collection of 82 lantern slides showing images of battles and devastation.
During the time of the Paris Peace Conference of 1919, Constantine organized a convention in Washington, DC of the friends of Greece to support Greek claims to territories in Thrace and Asia Minor. When Greece entered a war with Turkey in the early 1920s, Constantine spent much of his time in the U.S. pleading Greece's cause while the country went through not only the war but also political instability related to the struggle of monarchism versus republicanism. Constantine became a fervent supporter of the Greek Liberal Party's leader, Eleutherios Venizelos (1864-1936). Venizelos clashed with King Constantine during the First World War over the king's neutralist policies; the king had been deposed in 1917, restored to the throne in 1920, and deposed again in 1922, this time permanently. The clash between the two men had caused a fissure in Greek politics, pitting Venizelists against those loyal to the king; and this acrimonious situation continued as Greece's foreign policies seemed to be disintegrating after the king's restoration in 1920.
In the U.S., Constantine Moustakis helped organize a group called Greek Liberals in America with the purpose of assisting Eleutherios Venizelos, whose political life went through many crises and vicissitudes as he rose and fell in the position of prime minister. To support Greece as well as Venizelos, Constantine was instrumental in the publication of a newspaper entitled Bulletin of the Greek Liberals in America. When Venizelos, out of power, visited the United States in 1922, Constantine served as a kind of advisor and often accompanied him. Constantine's alliance with the Venizelist cause was clear during these years when Venizelos' former secretary, Kyriakos Tsolianos, and his sister, Asemina, would visit the Moustakis family during the summer at their beach home at Old Orchard Beach, ME.
Constantine was also active in the state and later in the national Republican Party. He soon became acquainted with Senator Warren Harding, whom he visited at Marion, OH, to take part in what became the famous "Front Porch" campaign which ended with Harding's election as president. Constantine first knew Calvin Coolidge when he was governor of Massachusetts. Later as president, he and Mrs. Coolidge received Constantine at the White House. Constantine was particularly pleased when the president mentioned that the two men were connected by marriage because Coolidge was also descended from the Putnam family of Salem as had been Constantine's late wife.
On April 30, 1924, Constantine was knighted by the Greek government, receiving the Grand Cross of the Chevalier of the Royal Order of King George I for services rendered to Greece in seeking better terms for Greece after the country went through a terrible defeat in the Greco-Turkish War of the early 1920s.
Constantine is said to have had an extraordinarily imposing presence which was noted by many people. His brother Nicholas once told their nephew George Marcopoulos a story that attested to this presence. During the Balkan Wars when both men were just ordinary soldiers they once were walking down building steps where many Greeks officers were standing. Much to Nicholas' amazement, as Constantine walked through, the officers incredibly kept stepping aside to make way for him to pass. A similar presence was evident also to many of his American friends who called him by his nick-name of "The Count," though he never claimed any noble descent. Constantine Moustakis died at his home at 11 Winter Street, Salem, MA, on April 15, 1925.
(A more complete biography can be found in the collection documentation folder.)
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Foreign affairs; Social justice; Moustakis, Christy Constantine; Moustakis, Gertrude Putnam; Moustakis, Constantine Christou; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940.
- Correspondence and family material, 1880 -- 2006; 1909 -- 1998; MS082.001; 3.15 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains personal papers and correspondence of Constantine C. Moustakis with various family members, especially letters written to his wife during his military sojourn in Greece; field notes and press releases to American newspapers as war correspondent describing battles and atrocities during the Balkan Wars; notes and various transcripts of lectures on the Balkan Wars delivered by Constantine Moustakis in Salem and Boston; correspondence of Constantine Moustakis with Greek political societies and American politicians promoting the post-World War I political agenda of Greece regarding territorial conquests; correspondence regarding gifts of chocolate; correspondence and material regarding the Moustakis Knighthood Banquet at the Copley Plaza in 1924; correspondence regarding sudden death of Constantine Moustakis and 'In Memorium' booklet; personal and genealogical material including Constantine's marriage certificate, medals, scrapbook, and last will and testament of Constantine Moustakis.
  This series also contains personal papers and correspondence of Christy C. Moustakis, and in regards to his sojourn in 1938 at Leon Trotsky's compound located at Coyoacan, Mexico; letters from Leon Trotsky to Christy Moustakis; correspondence regarding the films Christy Moustakis took of Trotsky while in Mexico; and obituaries of Christy Moustakis.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Genealogical material, MS082.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Constantine C. Moustakis, personal material and medals, 1902 -- 1914; MS082.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Drawing of Constantine Moustakis, MS082.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Wife, Gertrude Putnam Moustakis, 1908 -- 1918; MS082.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Drawings by Gertrude R. Putnam, (Mrs. Constantine C. Moustakis), MS082.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
    These drawings were preserved for many years at 11 Winter Street, Salem, MA by her sister-in-law Urania C. Moustakis Marcopoulos.
  - Correspondence of Gertrude Putnam Moustakis, 1910 -- 1918; MS082.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with wife and son during voyage to Greece, 1912 -- 1913; MS082.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
    These letters were kept in a vault at a bank in Salem, MA until July, 2003. The missing stamps from all envelopes were removed by Christy C. Moustakis for stamp collection.
  - Correspondence with wife and son during military sojourn in Greece, 1913; MS082.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with wife and son during military sojourn in Greece, 1913; MS082.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with wife and son during military sojourn in Greece, 1913; MS082.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with wife and son during military sojourn in Greece, 1913; MS082.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with wife and son during military sojourn in Greece, 1913; MS082.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with wife and son during military sojourn in Greece, 1913; MS082.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with wife and son during military sojourn in Greece, 1913; MS082.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with wife and son during military sojourn in Greece, 1913; MS082.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Children, 1919 -- 1924; MS082.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
  - Letter to Christy C. Moustakis from William MacBrayne, 1916; MS082.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - Field notes during Balkan War, 1913; MS082.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
  - Press releases during Balkan War, 1913; MS082.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
  - Journal of military sojourn in Greece, 1913; MS082.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
  - Writings and notes on Balkan War, unpublished, MS082.001.001.00021 (Box 1)
  - Lectures on the Balkan War, MS082.001.001.00022 (Box 1)
  - Lecture on the Balkan War to accompany the lantern slides, MS082.001.001.00023 (Box 1)
  - Political correspondence, 1907 -- 1919; MS082.001.001.00024 (Box 1)
  - Political correspondence, 1920; MS082.001.001.00025 (Box 1)
  - Political correspondence, 1921; MS082.001.001.00026 (Box 1)
  - Political correspondence, 1922; MS082.001.001.00027 (Box 1)
  - Political correspondence, July 7 to December 29, 1922, MS082.001.001.00028 (Box 1)
  - Political correspondence, 1923; MS082.001.001.00029 (Box 1)
  - Political correspondence, 1923; MS082.001.001.00030 (Box 1)
  - Political correspondence, 1924; MS082.001.001.00031 (Box 1)
  - Political correspondence, 1924; MS082.001.001.00032 (Box 1)
  - Political correspondence, 1924; MS082.001.001.00033 (Box 1)
  - Political correspondence, 1924 -- 1925; MS082.001.001.00034 (Box 1)
  - Transcribed letters of Constantine Moustakis and Gertrude Putnam Moustakis, 1913 -- 1918; MS082.001.001.00035 (Box 1)
    Transcribed by Edward W. Hanson.
  - Transcribed journal of Constantine Moustakis' military sojourn in Greece, 1913; MS082.001.001.00036 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Eleftherios K. Venizelos (Prime Minister of Greece), 1922; MS082.001.002.00001 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Letter to Eleftherios Venizelos from Constantine Moustakis, 1920; MS082.001.002.00002 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Correspondence regarding receiving Greek Honor of the Chevalier, Wednesday, 1924; MS082.001.002.00003 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Correspondence of regrets for Greek Honor dinner held on Wednesday, 1924; MS082.001.002.00004 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Correspondence of appreciation for gifts of chocolate, MS082.001.002.00005 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
    No Date Available.
  - Correspondence, MS082.001.002.00006 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Drafts of correspondence, MS082.001.002.00007 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
    Extremely fragile. No Date Available.
  - Assorted calling cards, tickets, receipts, pamphlets and booklets, MS082.001.002.00008 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
    No Date Available
  - Last will and testament of Constantine C. Moustakis, proved, 1925; MS082.001.002.00009 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - In memorium - Constantine C. Moustakis, 1883 -- 1925; MS082.001.002.00010 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Correspondence of Nichols C. Moustakis, 1880 -- 1969; MS082.001.002.00011 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Correspondence of Urania Moustakis and wedding invitation of April 24, 1930; MS082.001.002.00012 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Correspondence from Leon Trotsky to Christy C. Moustakis, 1939 -- 1940; MS082.001.002.00013 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
    These letters were found by Christy Moustakis' wife among his effects.
  - Correspondence of Christy C. Moustakis, 1964 -- 1982; MS082.001.002.00014 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Correspondence of Christy C. Moustakis, mostly regarding his films of Trotsky, 1986 -- 1988; MS082.001.002.00015 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Correspondence of Christy C. Moustakis, mostly regarding his films of Trotsky, 1988 -- 1989; MS082.001.002.00016 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Obituaries of Christy C. Moustakis, MS082.001.002.00017 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Beals, Charleton, "The New Genre of Roberto De La Selva," Mexico, 1937; MS082.001.002.00018 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Inventory of books on Trotsky and Marxism once owned by Christy C. Moustakis, MS082.001.002.00019 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Letters to George Marcopoulos from the Prime Minister of Greece and King Constantine II, 2005 -- 2006; MS082.001.002.00050 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
    This folder contains a letter to George Marcopoulos from the Prime Minister of Greece following his participation in Tufts commencement ceremonies in 2005 and a letter from King Constantine II of Greece congratulating Professor Marcopoulos on his 2006 retirement. These letters were donated to DCA by George Marcopolis in 2008 (2008.084).
  - Constantine Moustakis - biographical, 2003; MS082.001.002.00052 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
    This folder contains biographical sketches written by George. C. Marcopoulos, including one sketch entitled: "Miss Mabel Hill and the education of the Moustakis brothers," about Constantine and Nicholas "Nick" Moustakis.
  - Christy C. Moustakis - biographical, 1990 -- 2003; MS082.001.002.00053 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
    This folder contains biographical sketches written by George. C. Marcopoulos. It also contains one obituary/memoir written by Demila Jenner, "Portrait of Chris."
  - Notes on Moustakis Correspondence, 2002; MS082.001.002.00054 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
    Contains background information on Eleutherios (Eleftherios) Venizelos, Kyriakos Tsolainos, and Michael Tsmados compiled by George Marcopoulos. Also contains notes on three postcards written by Constantine Moustakis to his daughter and sister.
  - Correspondence re: Christy's Trotsky film, 1988 -- 1991; MS082.001.002.00055 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
    Contains letters sent from George C. Marcopoulos and Liz Moustakis (widow of Chrisy Moustakis) to David Weiss, Alexander Buchman, Eleanor Clark, and others. See folders 00015 and 00016 for more correspondence re: Christy Moustakis' Trotsky films.
  - Correspondence re: Christy's Trotsky film, 1991 -- 2002; MS082.001.002.00056 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Scrapbook of Constantine C. Moustakis, 1913 -- 1920; MS082.001.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - Constantine Moustakis- obituaries and letters of condolence, 1925; MS082.001.007.00001 (Box MS082 Shared 2)
  - White House memorandum on Greek affairs, 1922; MS082.001.007.00002 (Box MS082 Shared 2)
  - Gertrude Putnam Moustakis Journal, 1917; MS082.001.007.00003 (Box MS082 Shared 2)
  - Gertrude Putnam Moustakis - personal material, 1911 -- 1918; MS082.001.007.00004 (Box MS082 Shared 2)
  - Gertrude Putnam Moustakis - obituaries and letter of condolence [Death of Gertrude Putnam Moustakis], 1918; MS082.001.007.00005 (Box MS082 Shared 2)
- Photographs and films, 1905 -- 2006; 1910 -- 1998; MS082.002; 3.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains personal photographs of various Moustakis family members, formally taken as well as family 'snapshots' at home, at play, and on vacation in Greece; photographs of military and political events in which Constantine Moustakis was involved; 82 glass slides of battles and atrocities during the Balkan Wars used by Constantine Moustakis in his lectures; autographed photograph of Greek Prime Minister Eleftherios Venizelos; and an oversized, wide-angled photograph of Moustakis' Knighthood Banquet.
  This series also contains photographs taken of and by Christy Moustakis while staying at Leon Trotsky compound located at Coyoacan, Mexico; videotape cassette copy of original footage of Leon Trotsky in Mexico, using some of Christy Moustakis' original films spliced with the films of Alexander Buchman from their time as guards at the Trotsky compound. This series also contains three documentary films about Leon Trotsky, collected by George C. Moustakis.
  This series also contains a photograph of the former King and Queen of Greece, given to George Marcopoulos in 2001.
  - Postcard of Salem, Massachusetts, MS082.002.002.00020 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Moustakis' Bros. "Palace of Sweets", 1905; MS082.002.002.00021 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Serbian wars, 1912 -- 1913; MS082.002.002.00022 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Moustakis family, MS082.002.002.00023 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of other relations and unidentified, MS082.002.002.00024 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Christos G. Moustakis, MS082.002.002.00025 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Nicholas C. Moustakis, MS082.002.002.00026 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Constantine C. Moustakis, MS082.002.002.00027 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Gertrude Putnam Moustakis, MS082.002.002.00028 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Louis C. Moustakis, MS082.002.002.00029 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of John C. Moustakis, MS082.002.002.00030 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Urania Moustakis Macropolous, MS082.002.002.00031 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Priscilla C. Moustakis, MS082.002.002.00032 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Moustakis family trip to Greece, 1920; MS082.002.002.00033 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Christy C. Moustakis, MS082.002.002.00034 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Eleftherios K. Venizelos (Prime Minister of Greece), MS082.002.002.00035 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs taken with Warren G. Harding at Marion, Ohio, MS082.002.002.00036 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs taken with Calvin Coolidge, MS082.002.002.00037 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs taken at Washington, D.C., MS082.002.002.00038 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Trotsky compound at Coyoacan, Mexico, MS082.002.002.00039 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Leon Trotsky, 1939; MS082.002.002.00040 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Videocassette of Christy Moustakis' films of Leon Trotsky, MS082.002.002.00041 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
  - Photograph of former King and Queen of Greece, 2001 -- 2006; MS082.002.002.00049 (Box MS082 Shared 1)
    These items belonged to George Marcopoulos, and were donated to Tufts DCA in May 2008. Folder contains a photograph of former King and Queen of Greece given to Marcopoulos by students in 2001.
  - Appointment, MS082.002.003.00001 (Box 3)
    lantern slide
  - Certified, MS082.002.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Untitled, MS082.002.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Discharge, MS082.002.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - ? Officers (Broken), MS082.002.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Soldiers, MS082.002.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Battlefield at Lachana, MS082.002.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Lachana, MS082.002.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Lachana, MS082.002.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - Battlefield at Lachana, MS082.002.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Greek artillery maneuvering for position, MS082.002.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - Untitled, MS082.002.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - Cavalry fording stream, MS082.002.003.00013 (Box 3)
  - Jumayia Heights, MS082.002.003.00014 (Box 3)
  - Simethy, MS082.002.003.00015 (Box 3)
  - Halting troops, MS082.002.003.00016 (Box 3)
  - Tsayezie, MS082.002.003.00017 (Box 3)
  - Foraging party, MS082.002.003.00018 (Box 3)
  - Cresna Pass, MS082.002.003.00019 (Box 3)
  - Artillery: Cresna Pass, MS082.002.003.00020 (Box 3)
  - Cresna Pass, MS082.002.003.00021 (Box 3)
  - Cresna Pass, MS082.002.003.00022 (Box 3)
  - King on battlefield, MS082.002.003.00023 (Box 3)
  - King on battlefield, MS082.002.003.00024 (Box 3)
  - King at Demir Hissor, MS082.002.003.00025 (Box 3)
  - King at Livounovo, MS082.002.003.00026 (Box 3)
  - King at Livounovo, MS082.002.003.00027 (Box 3)
  - King and staff, MS082.002.003.00028 (Box 3)
  - King on way to battle, MS082.002.003.00029 (Box 3)
  - King and Premier, MS082.002.003.00030 (Box 3)
  - Bridge blown up, MS082.002.003.00031 (Box 3)
  - Officers and field telephone, MS082.002.003.00032 (Box 3)
  - Bulgarian officers, MS082.002.003.00033 (Box 3)
  - Bulgarian priests and soldiers, MS082.002.003.00034 (Box 3)
  - Bulgarians receipts, MS082.002.003.00035 (Box 3)
  - Return of churches to Turks, MS082.002.003.00036 (Box 3)
  - Doxato ruins, MS082.002.003.00037 (Box 3)
  - Doxato ruins, MS082.002.003.00038 (Box 3)
  - Doxato ruins, MS082.002.003.00039 (Box 3)
  - Doxato ruins, MS082.002.003.00040 (Box 3)
  - Doxato ruins, MS082.002.003.00041 (Box 3)
  - Ruins Nigrita, MS082.002.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Nigrita ruins, MS082.002.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - Nigrita ruins, MS082.002.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - Nigrita ruins, MS082.002.004.00004 (Box 4)
  - Nigrita ruins, MS082.002.004.00005 (Box 4)
  - Serras ruins, MS082.002.004.00006 (Box 4)
  - Serras ruins, MS082.002.004.00007 (Box 4)
  - Serras ruins, MS082.002.004.00008 (Box 4)
  - Serras ruins, MS082.002.004.00009 (Box 4)
  - Serras ruins, MS082.002.004.00010 (Box 4)
  - Serras ruins, MS082.002.004.00011 (Box 4)
  - Serras ruins, MS082.002.004.00012 (Box 4)
  - Serras ruins, MS082.002.004.00013 (Box 4)
  - Serras ruins, MS082.002.004.00014 (Box 4)
  - Serras ruins, MS082.002.004.00015 (Box 4)
  - Serras ruins, MS082.002.004.00016 (Box 4)
  - Doxato massacre, MS082.002.004.00017 (Box 4)